https://youtu.be/RS2KPkziRt8 This week, we're going to delve further into the question of where our ignorance comes
Thanh Loc 8/10 Minh Anh https://youtu.be/RS2KPkziRt8 Tuần này, chúng ta sẽ nghiên cứu sâu hơn câu hỏi: sự ngu dốt bắt nguồn từ đâu
from. We'll examine how individuals, groups, institutions, and governments strategically
Chúng ta sẽ tìm hiểu xem mỗi cá nhân, các nhóm, cơ quan và chính phủ
create and manipulate ignorance. There's plenty of material there for the most avid conspiracy
tạo ra và thao túng sự ngu ngốc như thế nào. Có rất nhiều tài liệu cho những người
theorists among you. But we're also going to tap into the ways in which ignorance gets
say mê theo đuổi thuyết âm mưu quanh bạn. Nhưng chúng ta sẽ không khai thác phương thức mà sự ngu ngốc được
constructed inadvertently, as we individually and collectively go about our ordinary activities,
xây dựng một cách vô tình, vì chúng ta dù là cá nhân hay tập thể đều lo cho hoạt động bình thường của mình,
exercise our preferences, and think our everyday thoughts. You may find that accidental ignorance
có những công việc ưu tiên và suy nghĩ riêng. Có thể bạn sẽ nhận thấy rằng sự thiếu hiểu biết một cách ngẫu nhiên
is even more intriguing than purpose-built ignorance.
thậm chí còn gây hứng thú hơn sự thiếu hiểu biết có mục đích.
For the first three lectures this week, starting with this one, I'm going to present material
Trong 3 bài giảng đầu tiên của tuần này, bắt đầu bằng bài giảng này, tôi sẽ trình bày tư liệu
on the ways in which ignorance is deliberately created and maintained via political and social
theo cách mà sự thiếu hiểu biết được tạo ra một cách có chủ đích và duy trì thông qua
processes. The fourth and fifth lectures will explore ways in which ignorance is implicitly
những quá trình chính trị và xã hội. Bài giảng thứ 4 và thứ 5 sẽ trình bày cách mà sự thiếu hiểu biết hình thành
or inadvertently generated or maintained via culture, preferences, and social norms. The
một cách tình cờ hoặc ẩn ý hoặc được duy trì thông qua văn hoá, ưu đãi và các quy tắc xã hội.
sixth, final lecture will examine the question of whether ignorance can be thought of as
Buổi thứ 6, bài giảng cuối cùng, sẽ trình bày câu hỏi liệu người ta có xem sự thiếu hiểu biết như
a "public problem" and, if so, whether there are any solutions for it.
một "vấn đề chung" và, nếu có, liệu có giải pháp nào cho chuyện này hay không.
In addition to withholding information, proliferating disinformation, and inhibiting curiosity,
Bên cạnh việc che giấu thông tin, lan truyền thông tin sai lệch và ngăn chặn sự tò mò,
there's another way we can impose ignorance on others, and that's by undoing their knowledge
vẫn còn một cách khác mà chúng ta có thể áp đặt sự thiếu hiểu biết lên người khác, đó là bằng cách xoá bỏ sự hiểu biết của họ
and sowing doubt. We can convince people that what they thought they knew they don't really
và gieo rắc nghi ngờ. Chúng ta có thể thuyết phục người khác rằng họ không thực sự biết về những điều mà họ nghĩ, họ biết.
know. We can create uncertainty or doubt where there wasn't any, or we can amplify existing
Chúng ta có thể tạo ra sự không chắc chắn hoặc sự nghi ngờ dù trong tình thế không đáng nghi, hoặc chúng ta có thể phóng đại
doubts. The manufacture of doubt turns out to be a widely practiced stratagem, especially
những mối nghi ngờ vốn có. Việc tạo ra nghi ngờ trở thành một mưu mẹo được nhiều người áp dụng, đặc biệt
in politically-charged topics. In order for seeding doubts to have the desired
là trong các chủ đề về chính trị. Để việc gieo rắc hạt giống nghi ngờ có hiệu quả
effect, it has to be acceptable to raise them in the first place. In some religious or political
như mong đợi, việc tạo ra nghi ngờ phải có thể chấp nhận được ngay từ đầu. Chẳng hạn, trong vài bối cảnh về tôn giáo
settings, for example, raising doubts about fundamental beliefs or values is regarded
hay chính trị, gây nghi ngờ về những niềm tin hay giá trị cơ sở được xem là
as heresy and therefore impermissible. In other settings, raising doubts is the norm.
dị giáo, vì thế mà bị cấm đoán. Trong bối cảnh khác, gây nghi ngờ là một quy tắc.
At first glance, social norms advocating this may seem scarce, but it's a matter of knowing
Thoạt nhìn, những quy cách xã hội dùng để biện hộ cho việc này có thể rất hiếm, nhưng đây là vấn đề của việc biết
where to look. Criminal trials in Western courts of law are one example. A defendant
nhìn nhận ở đâu. Những vụ hình sự trong các phiên toà miền Tây là một ví dụ. Một bị cáo
is to be convicted only if guilt can be demonstrated beyond reasonable doubt, so the primary job
bị tuyên án là có tội chỉ khi người ta có thể chứng minh tội lỗi đó vượt ra nghi ngờ hợp lý, vì vậy công việc chủ yếu
of the defense is to raise doubts about the defendant's guilt. Another example is in communities
của bên bào chữa là đề cập đến những mối nghi ngờ về tội của bị cáo. Một ví dụ khác là trong những cộng đồng
of scientists and scholars, where ideals of informed skepticism and critique can dominate
các nhà khoa học và học giả, nơi mà những điều lý tưởng của chủ nghĩa hoài nghi và phê bình chiếm ưu thế
so that any offering of new knowledge must pass trials-by-fire of intense scrutiny and
đến mức bất kỳ việc đưa ra kiến thức mới nào cũng phải vượt qua thử thách cam go, được các chuyên gia xem xét kỹ lưỡng
counter-argumentation by experts before it is published.
và phản biện trước khi tri thức mới được công bố.
These ideals and norms can, of course, be utilized for political ends. In his 1995 book
Dĩ nhiên, những ý tưởng và chuẩn mực có thể được sử dụng vì mục đích chính trị. Trong quyển sách năm 1995
"Cancer Wars", Robert Proctor documented the influences of professional, economic, and
"Cancer Wars" của mình, Robert Proctor đã cung cấp tư liệu về những ảnh hưởng của những nhóm lợi ích về nghề nghiệp, kinh tế
political interest groups on American governmental priorities and funding of cancer research.
và chính trị trong những ưu tiên từ chính phủ Mỹ và trong việc tài trợ cho nghiên cứu điều trị ung thư.
One of his primary findings was that the American government collaborated with private enterprise
Một trong những phát hiện chính của ông là chính phủ Mỹ hợp tác với các công ty tư nhân
in generating doubt about the environmental and industrial causes of cancer.
để gây nghi ngờ về những nguyên nhân liên quan đến môi trường và công nghiệp dẫn tới ung thư.
David Michaels' 2005 article in "Scientific American" and his 2008 book on the manufacture
Theo sau Proctor là bài viết "Scientific American" năm 2005 của David Michael và quyển sách năm 2008 của ông về sự hình thành
of doubt followed Proctor's lead. He identified three primary messages orchestrated by the
nghi ngờ. Ông đã xác định 3 thông điệp chính được ngành công nghiệp thuốc lá dàn dựng nên
tobacco industry to challenge the scientific consensus linking smoking with lung cancer.
nhằm thách thức những quan điểm khoa học chung nhất cho rằng hút thuốc là có liên quan đến ung thư phổi.
First, argue that cause-effect relationships have not been established. Second, claim that
Đầu tiên, tranh luận rằng mối quan hệ nguyên nhân kết quả không được thiết lập. Thứ hai, khẳng định rằng
statistical analyses are inconclusive. Third, emphasize that more research is needed before
những phân tích về số liệu không mang tính thuyết phục. Thứ bam nhấn mạnh rằng cần có thêm nghiên cứu trước khi
laws or policies can be adequately justified. This industry hired its own scientists, founded
những bộ luật hoặc chính sách được trình bày thoả đáng. Ngành công nghiệp này đã thuê những nhà khoa học của riêng nó, lập nên
its own research publication ("Tobacco and Health Research"), and carefully orchestrated
ấn phẩm nghiên cứu của riêng nó ("Tobacco and Health Research"), và dàn dựng chu đáo
a media campaign to spread their messages. More recently, Naomi Oreskes and Erik Conway's
một chiến dịch truyền thông nhằm lan truyền thông điệp. Gần đây, quyển sách năm 2010 của Naomi Oreskes và Erik Conway
2010 book on similar themes appeared, updated to include accounts of how doubts were manufactured
về những chủ đề giống nhau trình bày những nguyên nhân về cách tạo ra nghi ngờ
concerning climate change and global warming in particular by organizations employing tactics
khi xem xét đến thay đổi khí hậu và sự nóng lên của Trái đất, đặc biệt là cách thức của các tổ chức sử dụng số liệu
inspired by the tobacco industry's example. Frederick Seitz, a former president of the
lấy nền công nghiệp thuốc lá làm ví dụ. Frederick Seitz, cựu chủ tịch
National Academy of Sciences, was hired by the R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company to direct
Học viện Khoa học Quốc gia, được Công ty R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company thuê để điều phối
their Medical Research Committee. Seitz distributed $45 million in research grants to projects
Hội đồng Nghiên cứu Y khoa của công ty. Seitz đã phân bổ 45 triệu đôla trong trợ cấp nghiên cứu cho các dự án
designed to promote tobacco and therefore steering clear of anything that might impugn
được thiết kế để quảng cáo thuốc lá, nhờ vậy mà tránh được sự công kích
tobacco. In 1984 Seitz, Robert Jastrow and William Nierenberg founded the George C. Marshall
Năm 1984 Seitz, Robert Jastrow và William Nierenberg thành lập ra viện George C. Marshall
Institute, which then applied Tobacco Institute tactics of doubt-mongering to the issue of
rồi áp dụng chiến thuật Tobacco Institute vào việc gây nên sự nghi ngờ về vấn đề
climate change. They claimed that global warming was caused by natural variations in solar
thay đổi khí hậu. Họ khẳng định rằng sự nóng lên của trái đất bị gây ra bởi sự thay đổi tự nhiên
flux, and that any warming caused by greenhouse emissions is swamped by natural climate variations.
của bức xạ mặt trời, và sự nóng lên gây ra bởi khí thải nhà kính thì che khuất trong sự thay đổi khí hậu tự nhiên
The Marshall Institute on its Web site claims even today that there is no certainty about
Viện Marshall trên trang web khẳng định rằng ngay cả ngày nay cũng không có gì chắc chắn
the extent of human-caused climate change. Oreskes and Conway documented an elaborate
về mức độ thay dổi khí hậu do con người tao ra. Oreskes và Conway đã cung cấp tư liệu về
political and economic network of climate denialist scientists, with links to well-endowed
về mạng lưới chính trị và kinh tế về những nhà khoa học phủ định sự thay dổi khí hậu, với sự liên quan tới
"think tanks" such as the Heritage Foundation, the American Enterprise Institute and the
những "nhóm nghiên cứu" tốt cấp như tổ chức Heritage, viện doanh nghiệp Mỹ và
Competitive Enterprise Institute, and financial aid from trade associations such as the Electric
viện Cạnh tranh Kinh doanh, và hỗ trợ tài chính từ các hiệp hội thương mại như viện
Power Research Institute, the Global Climate Coalition and the Tobacco Institute.
nghiên cứu Năng lượng điện, Liên hiệp thay đổi khí hậu và viện thuốc lá
I won't go into further details of doubt-inducing tactics here; the sources I've mentioned do
Tôi sẽ không đi sâu vào chi tiết của chiến thuật gây nghi ngờ, nguồn thông tin mà tôi đã nhắc tới
an excellent job on that topic. Instead, I want to focus on an issue that supplements
đã làm rất tốt việc đó rồi. Thay vào đó, tôi muốn tập trung vào việc bổ sung thêm vào
the material covered by those sources. Machiavellian scheming and normative skepticism
vấn đề mà được che giấu bởi những nguồn thông tin này. Những mưu mô xảo quyệt và sự hoài nghe quy chuẩn
are not the only producers of doubt. Doubt also can be an unintended by-product of debate
không phải nguyên nhân duy nhất của sự nghi ngờ. Sự nghi ngờ có thể là sản phẩm phụ không cố ý của sự tranh biện
or balanced coverage of an issue. Journalists have been taken to task recently for giving
từ sự dưa tin có cân bằng của một vấn đề. Nhà báo gần đây đã bị chi trích vì
equal time to global warming disbelievers, on grounds that the scientific consensus is
cho những người không tin vào sự nóng lên của trái đất ngang thời gian xuất hiện, trên cơ sở  sự đồng thuận khoa học
so strong that lending credibility to disbelievers does the public a disservice. Holly Stocking
quá mạnh tới mức việc tín nhiệm những người hoài nghi này đã gây ra sự báo hại cho công chúng
and Lisa Holstein's 2009 paper presented a case study of the media coverage of a controversy
Bài báo của Holly Stocking và Lisa Holstein năm 2009 đưa ra một trường hợp tìm hiệu về độ phủ của phương tiện truyền thông về một vấn đề gây bàn cãi
following the rapid growth of industrial hog production in North Carolina during the 1980's
liên quan tới sự phát triển nhanh chóng của sản xuất heo công nghiệp miền Bắc Carolina những năm 1980 và
and 1990's. Their chief interest was journalists' responses to various attempts by the North
1990. Vấn đề họ quan tâm chủ yếu là phản ứng của nhà báo về những nỗ lực của
Carolina Pork Council to discredit and discourage a University of North Carolina public health
Hội đồng thịt heo Bắc Carolina trong việc không tín nhiệm và phản đối nghiên cứu của một
scientist's research regarding health and environmental problems arising from hog production.
nhà khoa học sức khỏe đại học bắc Carolina về vấn đề sức khỏe và môi trường gây nên bởi nền sản xuất thịt heo
Stocking and Holstein related four kinds of journalists' professional orientations to
Stocking và Holstein đưa ra 4 hướng đi của các nhà báo
the ways in which they treat conflicting views in scientific controversies.
trong cách họ xử lý sự mâu thuẫn trong tranh cãi khoa học
First, there is the journalist as disseminator, who is interested in ascertaining facts and
Đầu tiên, có một nhà báo là người tuyên truyền, quan tâm tới những sự việc xác thực và đưa
getting them to the public quickly. All viewpoints are to be presented impartially, regardless
ra cho công chúng thật nhanh. Tất cả các góc nhìn đều được trình bày thật công bình, bất kể
of any differences in credibility or status. It is up to the public to sift through the
khác biệt trong sự đáng tin. Điều này phụ thuộc vào công chúng sàng lọc
competing views and decide which are plausible and which not.
những góc nhìn cạnh tranh này và quyết định xem cái nào mới là chính đáng
Second, there is the journalist whose goal is investigating deeper interpretations behind
Second, there is the journalist whose goal is investigating deeper interpretations behind
the facts and providing useful context. This stance requires that the journalist make some
the facts and providing useful context. This stance requires that the journalist make some
independent judgments about what is credible or reasonable and what is not.
independent judgments about what is credible or reasonable and what is not.
Third, there is the populist mobilizer: Giving a voice to the public and influencing political
Third, there is the populist mobilizer: Giving a voice to the public and influencing political
agendas. Again, this orientation entails some independent judgments on the part of the journalist,
agendas. Again, this orientation entails some independent judgments on the part of the journalist,
especially concerning what the public needs to know.
especially concerning what the public needs to know.
Fourth, there is the adversarial journalist: Maintaining vigilance and skepticism of public
Fourth, there is the adversarial journalist: Maintaining vigilance and skepticism of public
officials and special interest groups. This role involves uncovering hidden interests
officials and special interest groups. This role involves uncovering hidden interests
served by public pronouncements or silences in scientific controversies.
served by public pronouncements or silences in scientific controversies.
The Disseminator and Adversarial roles are the most likely to raise doubts, but they
The Disseminator and Adversarial roles are the most likely to raise doubts, but they
do so in different ways. The Disseminator's pursuit of even-handedness can lend weight
do so in different ways. The Disseminator's pursuit of even-handedness can lend weight
to views that in other forums would be completely discredited. The Adversarial journalist, on
to views that in other forums would be completely discredited. The Adversarial journalist, on
the other hand, is more likely to raise moral doubts. For example, are the experts truly
the other hand, is more likely to raise moral doubts. For example, are the experts truly
impartial about the evidence? Do they have vested interests of their own?
impartial about the evidence? Do they have vested interests of their own?
Perhaps the most interesting finding in the Stocking and Holstein article was that journalists
Perhaps the most interesting finding in the Stocking and Holstein article was that journalists
with a high degree of scientific literacy were less likely to follow the equal-coverage
with a high degree of scientific literacy were less likely to follow the equal-coverage
rule-of-thumb and more inclined to evaluate the various claims and counter-claims, in
rule-of-thumb and more inclined to evaluate the various claims and counter-claims, in
most cases coming out in support of the scientists. An implication is that the equal-coverage
most cases coming out in support of the scientists. An implication is that the equal-coverage
rule also may function as a let-out for journalists who are ignorant about the science concerned.
rule also may function as a let-out for journalists who are ignorant about the science concerned.
In their study of American media, Max and Jules Boykoff found that more than half of
In their study of American media, Max and Jules Boykoff found that more than half of
all stories on global warming from 1988 through 2002 gave equal time to climate denialists,
all stories on global warming from 1988 through 2002 gave equal time to climate denialists,
with another 35 percent giving time to them while recognizing the consensus view. These
with another 35 percent giving time to them while recognizing the consensus view. These
journalists' uncertainties were then transmitted, wittingly or not, to their audiences.
journalists' uncertainties were then transmitted, wittingly or not, to their audiences.
This lecture has focused on the manufacture of doubt as a way of undoing knowledge and
This lecture has focused on the manufacture of doubt as a way of undoing knowledge and
thereby generating ignorance. We have seen examples of how this may be done deliberately
thereby generating ignorance. We have seen examples of how this may be done deliberately
and strategically, but also how it may be done inadvertently, even in the service of
and strategically, but also how it may be done inadvertently, even in the service of
a laudable aim such as balanced coverage of controversies by the news media. The next
a laudable aim such as balanced coverage of controversies by the news media. The next
lecture will broaden the scope of this theme by examining other kinds of strategic ignorance.
lecture will broaden the scope of this theme by examining other kinds of strategic ignorance.